<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rosenpass – Rosenpass</title>
    <link>https://rosenpass.eu/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Rosenpass</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	  <atom:link href="https://rosenpass.eu/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog: Post-Quantum Security in Avionics Paper Hackathon</title>
      <link>https://rosenpass.eu/blog/2023/avionics_july/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rosenpass.eu/blog/2023/avionics_july/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;Another week, another challenge. This time, Karolin, Wanja, and myself have spent the end of last week intensely working on a collaborative paper on improving the efficiency, security, and safety of Avionics cryptographic protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it currently stands, the process for updating the security of aircraft is a slow and labourious one. Certification of new standards can take years, and roll-out longer. This is, naturally, a problem in relation to faster-moving threats, such as those posed to cryptographic security. This academic paper, a joint collaboration between members of Rosenpass and the DLR (German Aerospace Center), proposes a method for significantly improving that situation by leveraging the partitioning principles already in use on aircraft to create a swappable, almost &amp;ldquo;plug and play&amp;rdquo; module to provide cryptographic functions on aeroplanes. The hope is to create a more responsive landscape for Avionics security, and help build closer ties between itself and Cryptography as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this end, a great deal of thought, and thus time, has been invested in mapping out the proposed protocols, structures, challenges, technical steps, and broader communication strategy in proposing this approach. Wanja Zaeske, a research scientist at DLR with strong contributions to the broader work at Rosenpass, spent the latter half of last week intensely working with Karolin, whose expertise in Cryptography needs no introduction, to iron out all the theoretical wrinkles in the paper. Meanwhile, Sven Friedrich, another research scientist at DLR, was hard at work, on Thursday, at producing a software demonstrator of the proposed protocols. My own role was to help with the argument constructions within the paper, and be an able English-language editor in the latter stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;card mb-3&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 90vw; width: 40rem&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://rosenpass.eu/img/wanja_karo_alice.jpg&#34; class=&#34;card-img-top&#34; alt=&#34;Photo of Wanja Zaeske, Karolin Varner and Alice Bowman&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;card-body&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h6 class=&#34;card-subtitle mb-2 text-muted&#34;&gt;Photography: Alice Bowman&lt;/h6&gt;
      &lt;p class=&#34;card-text&#34;&gt;From left to right: Wanja Zaeske, Karolin Varner, Alice Bowman&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satisfyingly, the in-person sessions proved fruitful in all directions. We were able to end Friday with a shared vision on all parts of the paper, and simply need to draft what was already agreed upon. We look forward to presenting the results of our labour in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog: NetBird and Rosenpass&#39; July Hackathon</title>
      <link>https://rosenpass.eu/blog/2023/netbird_july/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rosenpass.eu/blog/2023/netbird_july/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;Hello everyone and welcome to Rosenpass&amp;rsquo; very first blog post in what we hope to become a regular journal. This week, members of Rosenpass (Karolin, Ajuvo, and Alice) traveled to Berlin to meet up with NetBird, where we sought to build on the promising outcomes of our previous video conferences and establish a structure for deeper collaboration between our organizations along with a clear pathway to implementations of post-quantum security within NetBird&amp;rsquo;s services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://netbird.io/&#34;&gt;NetBird&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source peer-to-peer overlay network that automatically connects machines over an encrypted WireGuard-based tunnel. With NetBird, once a VPN connection is established, no data is routed through a server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the first day, Ajuvo and I were warmly welcomed to NetBird&amp;rsquo;s shared WeWork space, following initial meetings and technical work earlier in the day between Karolin and the NetBird team. After initial introductions, coffee, and cake, we were treated by Misha, their CEO, to a seminar on NetBird&amp;rsquo;s technical architecture and process, before Karolin took the lead in explaining Cryptographic principles and their applications to various areas of NetBird&amp;rsquo;s application. Both of these seminars paid close attention to scientific communication, hoping to provide clear and understandable explanations of complex principles as part of an ongoing commitment to making security technologies available to the greatest possible range of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;card mb-3&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 90vw; width: 40rem&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://rosenpass.eu/img/whiteboard.jpg&#34; class=&#34;card-img-top&#34; alt=&#34;whiteboard with notes from the previous seminars&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;card-body&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h6 class=&#34;card-subtitle mb-2 text-muted&#34;&gt;Photography: Alice Bowman&lt;/h6&gt;
      &lt;p class=&#34;card-text&#34;&gt;The combined notes from the two seminars&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following those preliminary explainers, the focus shifted to more technical questions, before Karolin and Maycon, their lead software engineer, got deep into constructing a working port of Rosenpass&amp;rsquo; Rust implementation into NetBird&amp;rsquo;s GO-based software. Meanwhile, Ajuvo, Alice, Julia (their product manager), and Kyle (an intern with NetBird) began to make plans for a tour of Berlin&amp;rsquo;s premier hacker space: c-base, including its fascinating and wild lore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the second day, discussions continued, as well as work on that port. By the conclusion of c-base&amp;rsquo;s tour, all were eager to continue work whilst soaking in the sun in c-base&amp;rsquo;s outdoor area, before eventually saying our goodbyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;card mb-3&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 90vw; width: 40rem&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://rosenpass.eu/img/c-base.jpg&#34; class=&#34;card-img-top&#34; alt=&#34;view of the river from c-base&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;card-body&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h6 class=&#34;card-subtitle mb-2 text-muted&#34;&gt;Photography: Alice Bowman&lt;/h6&gt;
      &lt;p class=&#34;card-text&#34;&gt;The view from c-base&amp;#39;s outdoor area in Berlin&amp;#39;s summer sun&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of the communal hackathons, meetings, and broader discussions, NetBird and Rosenpass had agreed on several collaborative projects, including the development of a full Golang implementation of Rosenpass, easing its integration into NetBird and further afield, with further work together planned for the future. We look forward to the continued growth of this promising relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
